{"tossups": [{"question": "The N\u2019ko alphabet was created for the languages of this people by Solomana Kante in 1949. The Muslim Dyula people are a mercantile subset of this ethnic group who follow the Suwarian Tradition of respectful dealings with non-Muslim neighbors. This people founded the Kaabu Empire, the last state primarily of this people, which fell after it lost the Battle of Kansala to the Imamate of Futa Jallon. A fanciful account of one ruler of this ethnic group claims he overcame his (*) childhood paralysis to defend his notably unattractive mother from an insult and later defeats a balafon-playing sorcerer-king of Sosso. Another ruler of this ethnicity brought crippling inflation to the economy of Egypt and the Hejaz during his hajj. For 10 points, identify this West African ethnic group whose most famous members are Sundiata and Mansa Musa.", "answer": "Mandinka people (accept Mandenka, Mandinko, Mandingo, or Malinke; prompt on Mande)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Mandinka people</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Mandinka people"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Mandenka, Mandinko, Mandingo, or Malinke; prompt on Mande"}, {"question": "One cartoon sees this character spanking Stephen Douglas while being told by Uncle Sam to \u201cgive him Stripes until he sees Stars\u201d. The first mention of this figure comes from the poetry of Phyllis Wheatley, though this character\u2019s name was coined in an illicit publication of a Parliamentary debate. Hedwig Reicher dressed as this figure in the Women\u2019s Suffrage Parade of 1913. The replacement of this character was facilitated by the issuance of (*) \u201cLiberty Bonds\u201d. The Vice President\u2019s entrance march is titled after this figure. Modelled after the French Marianne and British Britannia, for 10 points, who is this female personification of America who names a certain district between Maryland and Virginia?", "answer": "Columbia", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Columbia</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Columbia"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Dozens of alleged arsons were committed along the middle course of this river during a drought in 1839, leading to an outbreak of violence against local authorities by the peasantry. A 10th century traveler along this river observed the burial of a chieftain which involved a young woman having sex with the deceased man\u2019s subordinates and then being sacrificed by the \u201cAngel of Death\u201d. That traveler, Ahmad ibn Fadl\u0101n, wrote an account of his time as an ambassador to Alm\u0131\u015f (\u201cahl-moosh\u201d), the first Muslim king of a Turkic state named after this river. (*) Stenka Razin tried to capture the entirety of this river after pillaging a city at its delta. Feodor Chaliapin famously recorded a folksong about this river\u2019s boatmen and the cities of Kazan and Astrakhan lay on its banks. For 10 points, identify this principal river of European Russia and the longest in Europe.", "answer": "Volga River", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Volga River</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Volga River"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A story about the etymology of the name of this kingdom claims that it is composed of parts meaning \u201cchief\u201d, \u201cbelly\u201d, and \u201cinside\u201d because its king Dakodonu was derisively asked \"Should I open up my belly and build you a house in it?\" by a more powerful chief from whom he had requested land. A military unit in this kingdom began as elephant hunters called gbeto. This kingdom was briefly ruled by Queen Hangbe after the death of her twin brother, and in one account, she washed her genitals in front of the royal court to protest her deposition in favor of her younger brother. Under Agaja, this kingdom conquered the Kingdom of Whydah, leading to its subordination under the (*) Oyo Empire. This kingdom was defeated at the Battle of Poguessa, beginning its rule by France. Known for employing a corps of women known as its \u201cAmazons\u201d, for 10 points, name this West African kingdom centered in what is now Benin.", "answer": "Kingdom of Dahomey", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Kingdom of Dahomey</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Kingdom of Dahomey"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The early 16th century merchant Girolamo Sernigi wrote of how early Portuguese explorers were believed to be related to participants of these events. Funding for one of these events was diverted for the construction of the Great Bao\u2019en Temple. The first of these events was supposedly validated by a divine fire caused by the goddess Tianfei. One of these events supported Liang Daoming\u2019s control of (*) Palembang and defeated the pirate Chen Zuyi. Ma Huan wrote the Yingyai Shenglan based on his participation in three of these events. One of these events is claimed to precede Columbus\u2019 exploration of the New World by 67 years by Gavin Menzies. For 10 points, what were these events that occurred during the reign of the Yongle Emperor and were led by Zheng He?", "answer": "Zheng He\u2019s treasure voyages (accept Zheng He\u2019s voyages or descriptive answers that convey voyages of exploration/trade/diplomacy undertaken by Ming China)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Zheng He\u2019s treasure voyages</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Zheng He\u2019s treasure voyages"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Zheng He\u2019s voyages or descriptive answers that convey voyages of exploration/trade/diplomacy undertaken by Ming China"}, {"question": "While fighting at Taungdaw in Burma, one of these people killed 31 Japanese soldiers attacking his position despite losing his right arm and right eye from returning live grenades the enemy had thrown at him. Changlo Manor was renamed for this group after they successfully defended it as part of Younghusband\u2019s Tibetan Expedition. Singapore currently employs a group of these people as a counter-terrorist force. A subset of this group carries the Queen\u2019s Truncheon instead of colors, the only unit to do so, and has the motto \u201cBetter to die than live a coward\u201d. A war named after these soldiers was initiated by the (*) British East India Company partially for access to the cashmere goats of Tibet. For 10 points, who are these khukuri-toting Nepalese soldiers?", "answer": "Gurkhas or Gorkhas", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Gurkhas or Gorkhas</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Gurkhas or Gorkhas"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A harsh review of the American premiere of this symphony in the New York Post suggested that the title \u201cA Sleigh Ride through Siberia\u201d would accurately describe it. After a fermata, a timpani roll reintroduces the main melody played by the horns near the end of the finale of this piece. The celli are the second to carry the melody in this symphony\u2019s second movement after the opening oboe solo. The finale of this work features frenzied sixteenth notes in the strings under the low brass quotation of (*) \u201cIn the Field a Birch Tree Stood\u201d. Most of the brass notes in the scherzo of this work are written as sixteenth notes to match the exclusively pizzicato playing of the strings for that movement. Perhaps best known for its brass fanfare Fate motif, for 10 points, name this symphony, two before its composer\u2019s more famous Path\u00e9tique.", "answer": "Tchaikovsky Symphony No.", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Tchaikovsky Symphony No.</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Tchaikovsky Symphony No."], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Herodotus describes a city in this region as having \u201cpeculiarly alluring\u201d prostitutes, including the slave Rhodopis whose beauty convinced Sappho\u2019s brother Charaxus to purchase her freedom. Former pirate and Count of Syracuse Alamanno da Costa participated in a successful siege of a city in this region in which the attackers allied with Kaykaus I. The city of Tennis was founded on the brackish Lake Manzala, the largest in this region, by refugees from the similarly named city of (*) Tanis, also in this region. The Biblical Land of Goshen was in the eastern part of this region and where the Hebrews lived before the Exodus. The location of cities like Naucratis, Damietta, and Alexandria, for 10 points, identify this region where the world\u2019s longest river meets the Mediterranean Sea.", "answer": "Nile Delta (prompt on Egypt or Lower Egypt; do not accept or prompt on Upper Egypt)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Nile Delta</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Nile Delta"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on Egypt or Lower Egypt; do not accept or prompt on Upper Egypt"}, {"question": "The estate of Tiradentes, leader of the Inconfid\u00eancia Mineira movement, was subjected to this action after his arrest. Abimelech performs this action to his capital Shechem in the Book of Judges following a revolt, potentially as a means of carrying out \u1e25\u0113rem. This action was performed to the land of the Duke of Aveiro due to his participation in the T\u00e1vora Affair. Ashurbanipal did this action to (*) Elamite lands after conquering Susa. The most famous instance of this action was probably not carried out by Scipio Africanus during his most famous conquest. For 10 points, what is this means of making an enemy\u2019s land unsuitable for agriculture, most often associated with the Roman destruction of Carthage?", "answer": "salting the earth (accept equivalents; prompt on answers that suggest making the ground unsuitable for agriculture that don\u2019t mention salt)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>salting the earth</u></b>", "acceptable": ["salting the earth"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept equivalents; prompt on answers that suggest making the ground unsuitable for agriculture that don\u2019t mention salt"}, {"question": "A notable use of this weapon was important in the defeat of a force of monoxyla and Liutprand of Cremona provides the most trustworthy account of another battle featuring this weapon between the same combatants a century earlier. The Madrid Skylitzes contains a famous illustration of the use of this weapon and details its use during the rebellion of Thomas the Slav. Leo VI supposedly invented a handheld version of this weapon called a (*) cheirosiphones, which was later thought to be particularly effective against siege towers. This weapon was commonly used at the fore end of dromons and potential ingredients in this substance include pine resin, sulfur, and naphtha. For 10 points, identify this flammable substance of uncertain composition used by the Byzantine navy to ignite enemy ships.", "answer": "Greek fire", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Greek fire</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Greek fire"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The modern Mandarin word for a part of processing this resource is the same as the word for \u201cstir frying\u201d and Han-era texts describe another part of its processing as \u201charmonizing the hard and the soft\u201d. The presence of this resource is used as an archaeological marker of the Bantu expansion and its use at Ogoui in the Central African Republic, supposedly dating back to 2000 BCE, is controversially its oldest known processing site. A monument made of this resource shows signs of having been hit by a cannonball during an attack by Nadir Shah and was moved from its original location to the Qutb complex in (*) Delhi. This commodity\u2019s \u201cwootz\u201d variety was imported to the Middle East from India and was vital for Damascus\u2019 famous weapons. For 10 points, identify this commodity that\u2019s namesake \u201cAge\u201d followed the Bronze Age.", "answer": "Iron (accept steel)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Iron</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Iron"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept steel"}, {"question": "A poem written by this people against the rule of a warlord from Andijan defames his government for fleeing \u201clike pigs in the forest\u201d in the face of a powerful enemy and for its interest in virgins and dancing boys. Under the leadership of men like Khoja Emin, this people worked as local intermediaries in the genocide of their former rulers in the 1750\u2019s. The first ruler of a state named for this people rose to power with the help of the Karluks and Basmyls in a rebellion against the G\u00f6kt\u00fcrks, and that state gained many able bureaucrats from the Arab conquest of (*) Sogdiana. The Tajik soldier Yakub Beg founded the short-lived Kingdom of Kashgaria in the 19th century, which was mostly populated by this people, and their complicity in the Qing genocide of the Dzungars made them the dominant people in the Tarim Basin. For 10 points, identify this Turkic people who primarily live in Xinjiang.", "answer": "Uyghurs", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Uyghurs</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Uyghurs"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This man once disciplined a group of soldiers by making them jump into a lake in their underwear in winter and then fight a pack of wolves with their bare hands. This commander started his most famous campaign after breaking with his former commander Grigory Semyonov. This general\u2019s Asiatic Cavalry Division contained a group of Tibetans possibly sent by the 13th Dalai Lama who claimed he was an incarnation of the war deity Jamsaran. After taking Urga, he established the (*) Bogd Khan as leader of an independent Mongolia, but was soon captured by the Red Army and executed. For 10 points, identify this White Army general who attempted to recreate Genghis Khan\u2019s empire, also called the \u201cMad Baron\u201d.", "answer": "Baron Roman Nikolai Maximilian \u201cMad Baron\u201d von Ungern-Sternberg (accept Mad Baron before mentioned)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Baron Roman Nikolai Maximilian \u201cMad Baron\u201d von Ungern-Sternberg</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Baron Roman Nikolai Maximilian \u201cMad Baron\u201d von Ungern-Sternberg"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Mad Baron before mentioned"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s father served as a surgeon to the militia that lynched Joseph Smith. This man displayed a proclivity for writing while working for the New York Tribune under Whitelaw Reid and brought his experience managing the investments of this father-in-law Amasa Stone into his novel The Bread-Winners. With John Nicolay, this man was one of President Lincoln\u2019s personal secretaries. In a speech before Congress, this man claimed that American intervention in (*) East Asia was unnecessary. In his most famous post, one of this man\u2019s actions repudiated the Clayton-Bulwer Treaty. For 10 points, name this Secretary of State under McKinley and Teddy Roosevelt who negotiated the creation of the Panama Canal with Bunau-Varilla.", "answer": "John Milton Hay", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>John Milton Hay</u></b>", "acceptable": ["John Milton Hay"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Descriptive answer acceptable  The formation of Kietz settlements began during this process. When this process occurred far from other settlements, it was called \u201cwild rooted\u201d. This process facilitated the spread of the three-field crop rotation system and landlords called lokators were important in encouraging this process. Many places in Poland and the Czech Republic changed their name in the mid-20th century to reverse the effects of this process. Perhaps the most famous instance of this nonreligious process was the development of the (*) Teutonic state and it was used to justify the acquisition of lebensraum. For 10 points, identify this medieval process in which a certain Central European ethnic group settled throughout Eastern Europe.", "answer": "Ostsiedlung (accept answers suggesting that Germans are settling lands east of modern Germany)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Ostsiedlung</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Ostsiedlung"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept answers suggesting that Germans are settling lands east of modern Germany"}, {"question": "An apocryphal tale of a leader of this people claims that he invited his enemies to a dinner and then collapsed their benches while they were eating, making them fall into a pit of blades. This people carved the Rosemarkie Stone, a fragment of which is claimed to depict Daniel in the Lion\u2019s Den. The kings of the successors to this people are detailed in the Duan Albanach. The Kingdom of Frotriu was the most powerful state of this people, and under Bridei III it shook off Northumbrian oppression at the (*) Battle of Nechtansmere. This people were united politically with the Kingdom of D\u00e1l Riata under Kenneth MacAlpin. For 10 points, name this \u201cpainted\u201d people who lived in northern Britain, the predecessors to the Scots.", "answer": "Picts", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Picts</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Picts"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Two attempts were made to breach a defensive line at Fort Budapest in this conflict. The use of a Portuguese airfield in the Azores was crucial to the success of a supply effort in this conflict called Operation Nickel Grass. The site of a battle in this conflict became known as the \u201cValley of Tears\u201d after Avigdor Kahalani\u2019s forces held out against a vastly larger force. This conflict saw the first invasions by those involved in the formulation of the (*) \u201cthree no\u2019s\u201d of the Khartoum Resolution. A battle in this conflict got its name from the misinterpretation of Japanese writing on agricultural equipment and led to it being called Chinese Farm on Israeli maps. For 10 points, identify this 1973 conflict named for a Jewish holiday.", "answer": "Yom Kippur War (accept", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Yom Kippur War</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Yom Kippur War"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In a letter to his aunt, this man wrote, \"Man-shooting is the finest sport of all. There is a certain amount of infatuation about it; that the more you kill, the more you wish to kill.\" This man defended Nathan Bedford Forrest\u2019s actions at Fort Pillow, saying he witnessed no \u201cunusual bloodthirstiness on the part of the assailants.\u201d This man opposed the building of a Channel Tunnel because he believed that it would make it too easy for continental armies to invade. This general destroyed the capital of a kingdom after winning battles at Amoaful and Ordashu. Soon after that campaign, (*) this man was given command in the Zulu War, though the fighting was over before he arrived. This general who captured Kumasi may be most famous for leading the Nile Expedition that relieved the Siege of Khartoum. For 10 points, name this Victorian general parodied as Major-General Stanley in The Pirates of Penzance.", "answer": "Garnet Joseph Wolseley,", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Garnet Joseph Wolseley,</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Garnet Joseph Wolseley,"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In one game, a bust of this figure is a cheat character that can be spawned with the message \u201cWhere\u2019s my axe?\u201d and attacks via head-butting and breathing fire. After learning that Lisa does not actually like him, Ralph Wiggum gives a moving performance as this figure in a school play.  In a Youtube video, this figure claims to \u201ccock block more Scots than Hadrian\u2019s Wall\u201d while fireworks go off and soldiers dance in the background. In an adaptation of one of this figure\u2019s most iconic moments, undertaken on (*) Christmas, he was portrayed by Jeff Daniels in the TV movie The Crossing. This figure is depicted as the tyrannical despot of America in the Assassin\u2019s Creed III DLC after winning independence from Britain. For 10 points, identify this first president of the USA.", "answer": "George Washington", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "George <b><u>Washington</u></b>", "acceptable": ["George Washington"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Descriptive answer acceptable In one of these conflicts, a man called \u201cJack of the Feather\u201d by his enemies unsuccessfully tried to stop the founding of the town of Henricus. The second of these events opened with a massacre that killed 1/3 of one side\u2019s population. Ophecanough was the weroance of one side during the last two of these conflicts. The boundaries established by the final of these wars were reworked in the (*) Treaty of Middle Plantation. The first of these conflicts was fueled by the violent means by which Lord De La Warr ended the Starving Time. For 10 points, these were what series of early 17th century conflicts between the English settlers of Virginia and a group of Native American tribes led by Pocahontas\u2019 father?", "category": "History"}], "bonuses": []}